Raymond E. Biles collection, Inclusive: 1954-1973, undated, Bulk: 1957-1971
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Raymond E. Biles collection
Inclusive: 1954-1973, undated, Bulk: 1957-1971
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2619
Biles, Raymond E.
2 document boxes
The Raymond E. Biles collection consists primarily of newspaper clippings covering the educational desegregation era in Texas from 1956-1973. Also included is correspondence to Mr. Biles and other materials relating to his role as an adviser to the Waco Citizen’s Advisory Committee, which was tasked with reviewing local desegregation policies.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Raymond Biles was born on 1921 January 19 in San Antonio, Texas. He received bachelor's and master's degrees in Education from Baylor University and a doctorate in 1967 from the University of Texas. He taught in the Rosebud, San Antonio, and Alice school districts before beginning his 30 year career with Baylor in 1958. He was a member of Grace Temple Baptist Church. He and his wife Majorie had two children, Mickie and Ray. In addition to articles within his profession, Dr. Biles also collected editorial cartoons from 1965-1985 as a hobby. After his death in the spring of 1991, over twenty large boxes of these cartoons were given by his family to the W.R. Poage Legislative Library as the Raymond Biles Editorial Cartoon Collection. Biles also served on the board of the Waco Citizen’s Advisory Committee dedicated to providing support and a public voice to the desegregation efforts of Waco-area schools.
Scope and Content
The Raymond E. Biles collection consists primarily of newspaper clippings covering the school desegregation era in Texas from 1954-1973. The articles span topics such as school district desegregation plans, forced busing policies, court reporting on legality concerns, and many editorials commenting on the process. Also included are correspondence to Mr. Biles and other materials relating to his role as an adviser to the Waco Citizen’s Advisory Committee tasked with reviewing local desegregation policies. These feature such items as speech drafts and local petitions.
Arrangement
The Raymond E. Biles collection is arranged into two series, I. Desegregation and II. Citizen’s Advisory Committee (Waco).
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2619. Acquired 1984-11-21
Related Resources
Related references
“Editorial Cartoon Index — Biles Collection.” Accessed 2012 November 11.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Biles, Raymond E., 1954-1973.
Subjects
African American college students -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; African American students -- Texas -- Waco -- Attitudes.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Texas.; Citizen’s Advisory Committee -- Waco.; College integration -- Texas.; Discrimination in education -- Law and legislation -- Texas.; Minorities -- Education -- Texas -- Waco.; School children -- Transportation -- Texas -- Waco.; School Integration -- Texas; Segregation in education -- Texas.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Maps.; Research notes.
- Desegregation - Literary Productions, 1954-1973; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series primarily contains photocopies of newspaper clippings dealing with issues related to the desegregation of Texas educational institutions. Articles are sorted chronologically and placed in subseries based around major metropolitan areas. Articles that deal with multiple cities or Texas as a whole are located in the “General Texas” subseries. A small amount of other published materials such as magazines or pamphlets are also included. All non-photocopied items are generally in good condition.
  - Waco, 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Waco, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Waco, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waco (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Waco (2 of 2), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Waco, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Austin, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Austin (1 of 4), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Austin (2 of 4), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Austin (3 of 4), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Austin (4 of 4), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dallas, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dallas, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dallas (1 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dallas (2 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dallas (3 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dallas (4 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dallas (5 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dallas (6 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dallas (7 of 7), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dallas, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fort Worth (1 of 2), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fort Worth (2 of 2), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Houston, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Houston, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Houston, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Houston, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General Texas, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General Texas, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General Texas, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General Texas, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General Texas, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General Texas, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Texas, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Texas (1 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Texas (2 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Texas (3 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Texas, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Citizen's Advisory Committee (Waco), 1966-1973; 2
  This series contains a variety of materials pertaining to Raymond E. Biles’ role as a board member of the Citizen’s Advisory Committee in Waco. Generally items are divided into two subseries: Mr. Biles’ correspondence with concerned Waco citizenry and his own notes, drafts and professional materials concerning his work with the committee. Of particular note is a signed petition pertaining to a local redistricting issue. The materials are in good to fair condition.
  - Correspondence (1 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (2 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (3 of 3), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions: Drafts (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Literary Productions: Drafts (2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Literary Productions: Maps, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Literary Productions: Minutes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Literary Productions: Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Literary Productions: Notes (1 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Literary Productions: Notes (2 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Literary Productions: Notes (3 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Literary Productions: Notes (4 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Literary Productions: Petitions, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Literary Productions: Statistics, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)